[SPEAKER_01]: Shall we start?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does one lose recollectedness?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's start by reminding ourselves what recollectedness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you... how would you recollect yourself right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Recollect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: The basis for this experience, which might be, you know, I think, generally, I would go to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practically, if I tell you now, recollect yourself, what would you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Body.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would recollect something that's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: On its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why the Buddha referred to it as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The satipaṭṭhāna, the references for your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in fact, recollectiveness is more like just understanding something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing the reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing that which can serve as a reference point, which is your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practically speaking, oh, you want to be mindful, so you remember that your body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can descend it further and see, oh, this body is a necessary basis for any other experience I can have.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, you don't need to be looking at the specific experiences or even looking at the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to remember that the body needs to be there as a basis for whatever you're in currently attending to and engage with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only reason that you would forget that is because you haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, so that's that's my next question now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: If recollectedness, the reference point of your recollection, is not created by you, cannot be created by you, because you're not... my body is real only when I attend it to.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body is there which is why you can attend it to, which is why you don't have to attend it to.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just know it, to the extent necessary for the final knowledge, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the reference point is not in you, how can you lose your mindfulness then?
[SPEAKER_01]: By thinking that the reference point is in you, by misunderstanding, by not understanding the nature of... Of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: By being doubtful about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and how would that doubt set in?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, say now you're mindful, you're recollected of the body, and then you forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But does that change where the body is?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that change the nature of the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that change anything that can arise on the body as its basis?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the only thing that could change by you forgetting the correct reference point?
[SPEAKER_00]: By you forgetting... Let's try this.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not forgetting the reference point, say you calculate the correctness correctly,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're becoming more familiar with the nature of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: With its characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're allowing it to endure as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: As it is, which means you get to see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, forgetting about it is then within the reference point of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, forgetting about things, it's not how you lose mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about putting things in the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, when people think that when I forget about my body, that's how I stop being mindful of the body, they still think that the mindfulness is rooted in them attending to things, in them being the center of experience, not in finding the right reference point out there already enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as you hold on to the view that you are the center of your experience, which is already a form of conceit, you don't understand what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding that mindfulness is independent of you, because of these reference points of the body, feeling, thoughts, and the mind, mind and the thoughts, means sense of self, like self-centered point of view, is within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not first, it's not that which determines it, it's that which is determined by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then means you can forget all you want, your mindfulness remains undiminished.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you know your mindfulness is perfected.
[SPEAKER_00]: When forgetting about it, does not induce non-recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it cannot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, until you know that, that's basically the reason for you losing recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not having clarity regarding the nature of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because doesn't matter how much you forget, you cannot lose knowledge through forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which has been understood becomes impenetrable, becomes indifferent to whether you think about it or not, whether you get distracted by something else or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: The things you understood, you don't need to keep telling to yourself and repeating in order to keep that understanding, because the understanding has taken place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we've used the example before, if you know how to drive, you don't have to think about driving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every individual component of driving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't attend to that skill, that knowledge, then it's not as clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's what it's meant to practice to the... You're not such a good driver anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it's meant to practice to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not practicing mindfulness for its own sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're practicing mindfulness for the sake of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: This disenchantment, letting go of the world, which means the point will come, when you have practiced mindfulness to a sufficient degree, that there is no more basis for any passion to be maintained in your experience, and that's when you're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yes, you can stop practicing mindfulness then, but that's kind of impossible, because by that time you already... it wasn't your practice anymore, it was simply your knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're saying, so basically, the knowledge that you're talking about, the knowledge of mindfulness, or the knowledge of the body, or whatever,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's beyond a threshold whereby, if you forget about it... Yeah, it's completely... That's not an issue, that's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impenetrable by your forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you understand that that forgetting is still on the basis of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, furthermore, you get to understand that your lapsing in your mindfulness did not start when you forgot about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It started when you remembered your body again,
[SPEAKER_00]: on a completely different terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remember with confusion, remember with mother, remember with doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, is this the same?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it different?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it same or different?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it neither?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this the same feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, let me start again.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't start again, because you haven't started in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only find things being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can only continue.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, see, you prioritizing your idea of what mindfulness is and that my reference, my attending to things, that's where things originate, that's how it comes to be first, means you would actually ignore the fact the thing is already there enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you wouldn't be discerning it on its own terms, you'd be molding it into what you think it should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you lose your recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you get back to the same thing with confusion, with lack of understanding and lack of clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not when you forget about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how to maintain clarity?
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain clarity by understanding the reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that clarity is... it has nothing to do with whether you think about it or not, whether you're distracted by something else or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: The clarity of the understood phenomenon, understood nature of mindfulness of the body, remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you develop it, means, the harder for you will be to be confused about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The clarity can be developed, so that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's steady, it's clear all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what do you mean by all the time?
[SPEAKER_02]: As long as you are attending to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's not a clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity of understanding, not clarity of you attending to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you are attending to something,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness is the reference point that enables you to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you care about the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the clarity of the context is what the clarity of mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the clarity of your moment-to-moment attention, which is the result of the whole context that you now sacrifice on account of prioritizing what you are staring at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we also say that losing mindfulness, you lose recollecting this mindfulness, whatever, you lose it by not seeing the sameness?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to come to that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's take another, for example, reference point of the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is your current feeling now, overall, fundamentally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant, agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now we carry on talking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you forget about... Now, see, when you recollect the feeling, you kind of have a thought of what you're currently feeling, but you don't need to attend to it in order to keep feeling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason you can attend to it is because it's felt already.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you can turn your attention towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't want to be dependent on your attention, equally mindfulness, because it's actually secondary to the presence of that thing that you already kind of know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want that knowledge that you already have to start equaling mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, say you get distracted, you start thinking about something else, and now you want to re-establish your recollectiveness, and you ask yourself, what am I feeling now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, feeling pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is your attitude towards that reference point that you rediscovered, will determine whether your mindfulness lapsed, or whether it's still the same enduring, that has now included the attitude of forgetting this particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you get back to the feeling now, after having been thinking about it, do you think it's a different feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it the same feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have any idea where it was while you were not thinking about it?
No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where it was?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, where was it while you were not thinking about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did it disappear and then come back, the same thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, was it still there enduring?
Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the feeling, the reference point of mindfulness can endure then, unchanged, in its identity, so to speak, without needing you to attend to it constantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I'm feeling this, I'm feeling this, I'm feeling, feeling, touching, touching, moving, moving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to keep repeating that, yet it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's only the beginning of the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next time, you'll be less wound up when you forget about things, and you will not try to restart your entire practice,
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll just... no, I just need to recollect it correctly, because it was always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if you find out a different feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only different in its content.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of feeling remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's how you recollect it, determines whether there is the right context being established or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not whether you forget about it or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: The knowledge remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's that knowledge that you get to develop layer by layer by layer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the knowledge remains the same thing because...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dependent on your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that thing depends... that feeling, or let's say the nature of feeling, remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the knowledge is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in whether you attend to it or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the knowledge gets developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness gets understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think the tendency for most people is to prioritize their point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so, you might have... you might reckon, like, okay, I feel a pleasant feeling now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was feeling pleasant the whole morning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the tendency, I think, is to put first that what's changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's because it's it's rooted in that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you can impartially, externally, observe your experience without being the partaker in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, at the same time, while you're partaking in it, you can have this completely independent point of view upon your experience, point of view that's independent of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the idea of science, which is the idea of... common idea of when people say everything is impermanent, thus I am impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why people would then just... even when there is the same feeling enduring, they could not bear, they could not understand the idea of a thing enduring, unchanging.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They wouldn't say, well, it can't be the same feeling, because six seconds have passed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in my view, every second is a different entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you were to pursue their view, you would realize it contains a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's a millisecond within a millisecond.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you even utter a word and designate identity of something, if it's changing at every, like, those tiny microscopic levels?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, there can't be, in something enjoying the same, there can't be sameness without there also being change at a more particular level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was going to say that, that the point is not like, oh, I must...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about denying the fact that things endure for five seconds or ten seconds.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's to recognize that it's
[SPEAKER_00]: Your notion of the thing comes first, which is why you can discern the endurance of it, as in its particular change.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is no unifying identity of that thing, the change would not be perceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think that's what the mistake is, that people...
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting first, what's second?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people prioritize the more particular...
[SPEAKER_01]: The change.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more particular aspect which have changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is also... Because that's in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is, like, the kind of... First thing you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will remain on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will always be the first thing you see for as long as you also, uh, habitually act out of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can... That's also the first thing you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those... so you have to learn how to look at the periphery, like look at the background, because those particular changes can only be particular changes of a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you just need to find a reference point that remains the same throughout this change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not try to reinterpret the reference point through the change, but try to understand the change through the reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can say, oh, this morning I felt like this, then I felt like that, then he said something else, then it was this, then I done that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was unchanged through that?
[SPEAKER_00]: It was, oh, the something that I... the fact that my body was there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of my body was unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is unchanged through all the different postures, all the different bodily actions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of the body is unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is exactly why you can discern all these, like, exactly, sub-general, more particular changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, no, you choose to put that first and say that I have the body because of all of these molecular changes in constant elements that I can only observe because I have the body first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's reductionism.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everything can be reduced to the most particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people try to understand the nīcā through the same kind of lens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying, yeah, look, everything is constant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look, things disappear, thus they're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, impermanence is only to be discovered.
[SPEAKER_00]: When things are not disappeared, while you're still alive, that's the only way you can understand impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you wait for death to be proof of impermanence, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not impermanence, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just another change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not freeing yourself from the fact that things will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're freeing yourself that you're constantly within the change and partaking in the change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will for as long as you put that first and don't see the nature of that which is changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, endurance is in the completely opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, impermanence is in the completely different direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in the direction of what is actually enduring, what's remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which actually, now I say, it sounds like a contradiction, it sounds like, but that's exactly where... That's where the sotāpanna is inside, is whatever has the nature of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because I also waited long enough to see it disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because it's right there and I get to see it and because that nature is present, I get to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because cessation is manifested, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impermanence is on the level of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, seeing that, the nature of, for example, body as being
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically, it's already enduring whether I attend to it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's got nothing to do with me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether I forget about it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the nature of that thing has nothing to do with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have no control over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where I'm coming from.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I keep putting that first, I will gradually undermine my own gratuitous sense of that I am first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the master controller of this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the development.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Development of the nature thing that will have to result in dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I keep saying in previous talks, you know, come back to the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You couldn't have left it even if you wanted it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the idea that you hold the view that you can return implies that you can leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, come back to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you still subscribe to the view that you can come back to it, it carries the implication that you could have left.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for as long as you hold that view, you'll never understand that whether you leave or go, you are dependent on the body right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your practice is to keep returning to the present moment, you are...
[SPEAKER_00]: Intentionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maintaining a wrong view that you can leave the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Removing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming that you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, ironically, keeps you away from the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, like, when you recollect it, it's not about attending to the body here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like understanding the body that is here, understanding the feeling that is here, understanding the mind that is here, understanding the thoughts that are here, as a necessary basis for everything else that I can attend on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you said, knowledge is to be developed, consciousness is to be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Consciousness, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness as the aggregate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because usually consciousness is where my point of view is, but then you realize, understanding that there is no such thing as an independent point of view, independent of the existing body, existing feeling, existing mind, existing thoughts, means there's no such thing as consciousness independent of the existing matter and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your sense of self, your self-centeredness,
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody denies that it's there, but you see it now a second, which means that's not the owner, that's not the master.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: When these things disappear, my sense of self cannot remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically experience of not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through denying that which is self, but seeing it is fully dependent on this, and you fully understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, lack of understanding means putting the... your point of view first.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a lack of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not understanding consciousness, not understanding aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's not go into aggregates now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's stick with the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, it corresponds to the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness is always that move, or like a move, that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the understanding, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, yeah, recollecting the conflicts that's been clarified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putting the right thing first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you need to have knowledge, you know, in order for mindfulness to be right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Samādhi always comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't know what the context is, how can you recollect it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you discern it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the idea of mindfulness for you is attending to my body here and now, means exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I don't attend to it, my mindfulness is gone, because that's the only mindfulness that I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the mindfulness is based on discernment and the knowledge, that can't go, because it's independent of what you choose to attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is protect the context, by not contradicting the context, through acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you said this before, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you realize if...
[SPEAKER_01]: You've forgotten the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that that forgetting is included within that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's secondary within the enduring body.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't possibly have been here having forgotten about my body if there wasn't a body here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter the extent of your forgetfulness, the extent of your remembering it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have understood the reference point correctly, it will be included properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you cannot be forgetful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is going beyond the threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's a kind of... Yeah, that's already stepping across the threshold of that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you're partaking that right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, even if you... if you got completely distracted with, I don't know, to do something that required, like, this full-on concentration, when you stop doing it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your context is back, because it could have never left, and you understood that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the context re... re-emerges, so to speak, you don't mistake it, you're not confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Your confusion in regard to the re-emerging context of your body being there on a necessary basis, does not induce you to think you are first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you have gone beyond the doubt as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when Buddha asked monks, monks, do you see this has arisen?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see this is manifested?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, we do, sir.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see that on account of that being manifested as a necessary basis, this comes to be as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, yes, we do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Monks, the one who is not clear that this comes first and this then comes second, is there doubt arising in their mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are not clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just doubt means confusion in regard to the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lapse of mindfulness means confusion in regard to the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it means that you could still... it's possible for you to still... as you... when you remember, suddenly you realize you've forgotten presence and body, there still remains a possibility for you to think that that loss was because you weren't paying attention to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it was you... your fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all...
[SPEAKER_00]: I haven't attended to it hard enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's... it's really... it's about learning how to forget mindfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not about preventing forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like even Vajrajan Chah describing one of his talks when he was practicing meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was all wound up trying to concentrate on his breath every second, every second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he just... you can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he said, no, what if I let my mind think?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he would let his mind think and he would go further and go further and keep a corner of your eye at it, at the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But inevitably, it will have to pass the point when you forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he would allow that to happen as well, and only stop it when that forgetfulness would then carry on and start thinking about lustful thoughts or grief.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something you cannot not be aware of, because it starts involving your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, now I'll restart.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not before that point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But usually people now restart every second.
[SPEAKER_00]: You restart for the sake of next restarting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean, like, when I kind of semi-jokingly say, it's like throwing an anchor, but you don't wait to be anchored.
[SPEAKER_00]: You pull it and then throw it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your purpose of anchoring is just to keep chucking the anchor into the water and not let it anchor you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to learn how to forget mindfully and then you will not be able to lose the context, nor will you be able to kind of drift into the sensuality, ill-will and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that requires choices that you make on account of the doubt, on account of the confusion regarding the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not on account of forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because if you can't accidentally, sorry, you can't accidentally just unaware...
[SPEAKER_00]: Get fully engaged with sensuality or start harming somebody physically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be on the level of choice that you would make if the basis is muddled.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you would... that's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't... you wouldn't make those choices if you realize that, no, that necessary basis comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be impossible for you to make those choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any unwholesome choice is always based on you trying to control
[SPEAKER_00]: The feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putting yourself first.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the master, thus I have every right to try to control this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why mindfulness, you can't have too much of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just recognition, but it's already there, and there can't be too much of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why restraint comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why restraint comes first, and that's why, for Arahant, mindfulness is completely effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he doesn't need to do it, but he cannot not do it, because it's not about doing it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: His discernment is on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it different?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's been like 15 minutes, and the same thing has been enduring in the background, even without you needing to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize... See, even if you don't explicitly think, oh, that feeling comes first, your point of view comes second as a result of it, your attention comes second, you already start to discern that it comes first because it was there independent of all of your movements, actions, thoughts, words you said, things you attended to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you just... the more you... you become familiar with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that familiarity you want to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when it goes away, it doesn't come back as a stranger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the familiarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thing that's always been there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means the whole setup comes back with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also why all you need to do, once you fully develop sensory strength, all you need to do is practice mindfulness and you won't be even pressured by sensuality anymore, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: See, when you cannot pervert the order that this feeling or this body comes first, you cannot then give in to what you want to attend as coming first, which is sense object.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter what sense object comes your way, you see it within this context that's actually...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if I engage with sensuality, this cannot change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you can't forget it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you can't engage with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires you to turn away from that context, but not just to ignore it, but to ignore it on the pretext of pretending, I am first, thus I will still do what I want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you also get to eventually understand that it doesn't matter the power and the extent of your volition and your will, this order can never change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you abandon your own choice, the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through that indirect recognition of the right order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but you can't make choices which are based on passion, killing someone, sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: And expect to maintain the right context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because that requires the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that right order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Takes away the passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the extent of the action that you just said, the extent of sexual intercourse, the extent of killing somebody, is... requires you being first, in your view, in your point of view, putting that first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires it as a basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we say because it's... because basically you're assuming that you have some level of control over your feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's that assumption of that control that... it's basically the extent of that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is required, to a certain extent, for you to act physically, either towards sensuality or towards karmic.
[SPEAKER_00]: You may have the assumption without acting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which needs to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to stop acting, because you stop fueling the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you get to understand the assumption, and once it's understood, it's gone, and then you cannot act like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, Arahant is incapable of sexual intercourse or intentional killing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because
[SPEAKER_00]: Those acts have lost significance and he doesn't even know what that is anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because he cannot, sort of, twist his mind to the extent necessary for those acts to be intentionally done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... it's not also because he's got... because of all that willpower that... No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's just got, you know... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he's understanding it's... No, it's just the mind cannot be perverted to that extent anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, alternatively, then you can, you know, if the feeling... Again, when I say the feeling, usually it should be discerned on the level of the mood, if you want to practically start developing what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, you can do your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is your current body posture?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever the body posture is present, means the body needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start understanding necessity of the body through the current body posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, again, we've been speaking for like half an hour or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind was going left and right, explaining different phasses, different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your posture has remained unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you didn't have to attend to it, and you didn't have to keep telling to yourself that you must be seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you forgot about your body posture numerous amount of times, yet the reference point of mindfulness is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you realize, ah, so it's really how I remember it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I remember it with that clarity, with the right context, if I recognize it for what it is, that's how you maintain your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by having the kind of, you know, the non-lapsing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: People think the idea is you just hold so tightly every second of your life for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: One-pointedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's completely opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just you're unable to not recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot mistake it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when mindfulness is developed to the extent necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I could focus on the fact that my posture is maybe slightly changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like
[SPEAKER_01]: Your arms have changed, your legs have changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within the same identity of the same seated position.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, could you say, if somebody... if you notice that you're suddenly in a different mood...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's in common to a good mood?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in common to a bad mood?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, make that move towards...
[SPEAKER_00]: Include...
[SPEAKER_00]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Include it within.
[SPEAKER_01]: Include the mood within the greater identity of the unchanged thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which makes it possible... For the mood to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...for those different things to be the same, to be a change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which makes possible, which makes it possible for a mood to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the current mood is the utmost, highest point of your mood, it could never change.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would remain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, good mood, bad mood, neutral mood, what's in common to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seated posture, standing, walking down, laying down, what's in common to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body having to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you get to discern the identity of the phenomenon of the enduring body
[SPEAKER_00]: Through being mindful of a particular context of your posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through, like, I'm seated, I'm seated, I'm seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nāma knees, nāma ankles.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nāma knees, nāma ankles, nāma feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't need to do that, because you already know where you are and what you are, and the designation of seated body already is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I ask you, are you seated now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you need to stop and think about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, start body sweeping from your toes to the top of your head?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would know, of course, I'm seated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just thinking...
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, just playing with this image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Playing with this image I have of what my body looks like spatially, based on the fact that I know I'm sitting down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be possible if I didn't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And practically, that results in you putting the image of where you think the body is first, and not what your actual body is, which is the basis for that image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you cannot be properly mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you cannot sustain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, the moment you forget about that image, you have forgot the only reference point you knew, which was not even a reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like trying to... trying to anchor your boat by throwing, like, the floating... those floating cones.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just stay on the surface of the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you float with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not anchored.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not discerning through what's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the surface, I see what I attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all I do is just keep clutching the surface.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, just not seeing the necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason you can attend to different parts of your body is because the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you already know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you're attending to your knees, you're not attending to your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: But attending to your head is a possibility in the background of your attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why you can then go and
[SPEAKER_00]: Turn to it and attend to the head.
[SPEAKER_00]: The space already, the nature of space is already a nature of possibilities in different directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already within the body being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the entire universe is contained within this body less than two meters tall, as the Buddha said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like when you sit to practice your meditation or your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about I must stay mindful with every second.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must learn how to forget mindfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to allow yourself to forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you un-forget it, you don't induce confusion about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do, that's will work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That confusion needs to be clarified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I might... Like, see, even if you're confused, you don't need to try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You include it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the body needing to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, your doubt and any of the five hindrances are then seen in the right light.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're secondary to the necessary base of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't give...
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't have the power over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But putting yourself first means putting the hindrances first.
[SPEAKER_02]: They become obstacles.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where they hinder.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to me that we... Just getting this include... including.
[SPEAKER_00]: Learning how to include.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Including the context that remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the necessary basis for the practice of including is discernment of the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, as I was saying, that maybe... maybe now talk the other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or maybe... Oh, somebody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: When, you know, like you hear this generic instruction, just come back to the present moment, just let go, just let things go through, and it works for a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It works initially, because the problem of your suffering is you resisting things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now there's this novelty that tells you don't resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't resist it, but then your context of it is still a context of resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you start resisting that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you come back to the present moment, works initially, helps you with whatever suffering, but then, oh, now you start doing that on account of trying to avoid suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not including it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say you must include it, people will include it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you want to include it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you want to get rid of that which bothers my point of view, which means my point of view is first and needs dealing with these particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start doing mindfulness correctly for the wrong reasons, which means it's not the right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see that your point of view is second, you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you wonder, oh my God, that will overwhelm me with anxiety and stuff, it might, which is why you need to develop sensory strength, precepts, unblemished virtue beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: A layman or a monk, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And pretty much, when you say that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of anxiety is possibly a good sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a good symptom, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are anxious only because you don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, no, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about knowing what I must do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about knowing what I will not do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you cannot be anxious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of being okay with not knowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You become okay, which means you're not anxious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you realize, no, I do...
[SPEAKER_00]: I know exactly what I want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all I need to worry about.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to worry about how will I figure this out, because I don't need to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason why I needed to figure it out is because I didn't know what I'm not supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, your mind drifts off.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you really remember that your body is seated here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same position.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the drifting, there was a way...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to use that as a... yeah, what if, what if, what if... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was within the body remaining unchanged all this time, even when I wasn't thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I wasn't practicing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have this sense of duty, sense of my... this is what I must do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that sense now, you don't need to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You include it in the body being unchanged, remaining in the same seated position when you sat down to meditate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you stop acting out of doubt, out of restlessness, out of worry, out of remorse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you get to discern the context that's beyond it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The necessary basis for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And saying, oh, I had a sensual thought, I had a sensual thought, within the context of the body that hasn't been acting sensually.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha says.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would get to understand these things because his behavior has been purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the body has been factually not engaging with these things anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes your new container, your new reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you get to approach it on the level of the mind eventually.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, as the Buddha says, knowing thoughts as thoughts, feelings as feelings, the body as the body,
[SPEAKER_03]: You're knowing... like, I've seen people, they meditate, and then they're like, oh, there was no more body, there were no more thoughts, I went beyond the mind, beyond the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's true, in a sense, that they went beyond what they think the body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that was a completely very, very limited perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you would get to understand what the body is, you realize, well, it's impossible for it to not be there as a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like saying, all the matter has disappeared, half of my aggregates were gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're just removing all the wrong views and assumptions you would have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: People think I must attend to the body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means seeing the body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means seeing the body within whatever particular is happening with the body, you still... the nature of the body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, my body is seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: My itching moving.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things of the body that you can attend are possible because the body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things within the feeling that you can attend on account of your feeling are because feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, feeling within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, discerning the nature and not being sort of gripped and losing the sight on account of the particular thing that pulled your attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like remaining impenetrable with regard to discerning the nature through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you say it's not just seeing the nature, but seeing...
[SPEAKER_01]: That any particular manifestation of this thing is within, is enclosed within, is subordinate to the nature of that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The relationship between the nature and the particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're just looking for the nature, it will become the new particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the entire bodhisattva upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't go into with what, what is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: These two things are present.
[SPEAKER_00]: With this,
[SPEAKER_00]: This has to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you say, say, with the particular, there is the nature, there is the general, there is the... Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Particular, as you say, is the first thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gets recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through which you discern the essence, because of which you realize that's why particular is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the two sticks propping each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why there is no ultimate saṅkhara you need to discern, or the ultimate nature, the true nature that underlines the entire universe.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's right here, in this body, less than two meters tall, in your actions, in your speech, in your thoughts, that principle needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And seeing that will uproot the passion from all these domains.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because seeing that it's these two things that are mutually determining each other,
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaves no room for the sense of self, the owner, that's first controlling them all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That depends on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I look at this, I see this behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I look at that, I see this behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, where am I?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever I am, I cannot be outside of this dependence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you already start practicing anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by denying yourself, but by including it in the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Order that is dependable upon these things that are not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practice of mindfulness is practice of mindful recollected forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning how to forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning how to forget mindfully.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without inducing... How to forget without... Yeah, learning how to forget without your forgetting inducing confusion and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's induced, you include it in the necessary basis that was necessary for your experience of forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning how to forget in the right order.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not perverting the order on account of your forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's actually impossible to pervert the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter whether you forget about it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being clear about it, you'll stop being wound up by your forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And equally, you'll stop acting out of passion on account of your forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you won't be forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And forgetting, though, just says the same lecture of anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have the experience of forgetfulness on account of the present body enduring here, present feeling enduring here, which you cannot forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, forgotten means it's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's in the sphere of knowledge, as we discussed that before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to go around thinking that two and two is four, two and two is four.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that always.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there, because it's part of the level of understanding now how two and two work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this, you understand the order, you're fully clear about the order, it's impossible to pervert the order through the confusion about the understanding, means mindfulness is effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: With two and two plus four, you don't keep meddling with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have this nervous sense that I've got to keep going back to it, because you realize that two and two and four, no matter what I do, there's nothing I need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'll just stop doing anything with regard to it, because I don't need, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you're experiencing, whatever you're meddling with, it's on account of the body being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on account of the feelings enduring there, unchanging their identity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they might be changing momentarily, while remaining the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on account of the mind being there, on account of the thoughts being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: The boys are restless.